Guide to the Neighborhood Centers Association Records, Pittsburgh, 1890-1954 AIS.1964.28
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Neighborhood Centers Association, Pittsburgh Records
1890-1954
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Neighborhood Centers Association (Pittsburgh, Pa.)
AIS.1964.28
6.25 Linear Feet (16 boxes)
The Neighborhood Centers Association, established in 1895 and incorporated in 1912, provided neighborhood centered services on the North Side in an effort to promote, encourage, and provide a means for individual and cooperative activities among residents of neighborhoods. The collection includes correspondence, minutes of the board of directors, records on Camp Bonsall, reports, settlement books and miscellaneous unpublished social studies and statistics.
History
The Neighborhood Centers Association, established in 1895 and incorporated in 1912, provided neighborhood centered services on the North Side. The purpose of the agency was to promote, encourage, and provide a means for individual and cooperative activities among residents of neighborhoods. It intended to help neighborhood residents in learning to live together and to improve living conditions for their individual benefit and for the betterment of their neighborhoods and the larger community.
Within the framework of this purpose, the aims and goals of the agency were, through the cooperation of neighbors, staff and board, to provide the atmosphere within which peoples of different nationality, racial, and religious backgrounds could work together in mutual respect by learning new skills and interests. This association intended to be the agency through which citizens could work together toward the elimination of blight and its deteriorating effects upon their lives. Members were given professional help to assist in the solution of problems affecting both family and community life in order to be able to recognize and involve potentail leaders within the areas served.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection includes correspondence from 1920-1949 and minutes of the board of directors. There is information regarding Camp Bonsall such as studies, statistical summaries, construction reports, petty cash reports, staff and work crew reports, camp projects and publicity. There are also reports, settlement books, and miscellaneous unpublished social studies and statistics. This collection includes records of the Woods Run Settlement House, a predecessor of the Neighborhood Centers Association which engaged in social welfare work on the North Side of Pittsburgh, in what was Allegheny City before 1906.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was a gift of the Neighborhood Centers Association in 1964.
Previous Citation
Neighborhood Centers Association, Pittsburgh Records, 1890-1954, AIS.1964.28, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Neighborhood Centers Association, Pittsburgh, Records, 1890-1954, ais 64:28, Archives of Industrial Society
Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Social conditions; Allegheny (Pa.) -- History; Associations; Social action; Neighborhoods -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Neighborhood Centers Association (Pittsburgh, Pa.)
- "Growth of Woods Run Settlement" by Jean A. Kravetz, Submitted to University of Pittsburgh, 1945. Master of Arts Degree. Woods Run Settlement House (Box 1)
- Allegheny Association for the Improvement of the Poor, 1895-97
- Work of Woods Run Industrial, Incorporated.
- By-laws of Woods Run Settlement
- Charter of Incorporation of Woods Run Industrial House
- Constitution of Woods Run Industrial House
- Agreements Ordinances - Woods Run Settlement
- Woods Run Settlement - Miscellaneous Correspondence
- Correspondence (miscellaneous), 1906-1922
- Miscellaneous, Correspondence Reports etc.
- Miscellaneous Board Correspondence, 1934, 1937-38
- Correspondence-Mrs. William Thaw
- Correspondence Reports-Jeanette Kennedy
- Correspondence-Jeanette Kennedy #2
- Jeanette Kennedy, Recording Secretary-Notes- reports, etc. #3
- Memorial Letters, Jeanette Kennedy
- Letters received during World War II from boys in the service
- Reports, Correspondence
- Final Committee Meeting Minutes, December 1, 1927 (Box 2)
- Miss Jeanette C. Kennedy-Board of Managers Meeting Minutes, 1941-1943
- Annual Meeting Minutes, 1917
- Miscellaneous Minutes
- Meeting Minutes, June 5, (nd)
- Meeting Minutes, May 6, 1904
- Meeting Minutes, July 20, 1915
- Meeting Minutes, 1919
- Meeting Minutes, 1926
- Meeting Minutes, December 14, 1927
- Annual Reports, (Miscellaneous) Center, Associations, Settlements (3 folders)
- Annual Reports, Woods Run Settlement (intermittent), 1911-1954
- Annual Meetings-Jeanette Kennedy, 1935
- Annual Meetings-Jeanette Kennedy, 1940
- Board of Managers Meetings, 1942
- Woods Run, Summary of Headworkers Report, May, 1907 (Box 3)
- Woods Run, Summary of Headworkers Report, November 25, 1912
- Woods Run, Summary of Headworkers Report, December 23, 1912
- Woods Run, Resident Director, January 12, 1912
- Woods Run, Digest of Report of Resident Director of Woods Run Settlement, February 26, 1912
- Woods Run, Resident Director, February 26, 1912
- Monthly Meeting Board of Directors-(Resident Director), April 29, 1912
- Woods Run, Director, 1947
- Woods Run, Treasurer, 1941
- Woods Run, Treasurer-Annual Meeting, May 26, 1942
- Woods Run, Jeanette C. Kennedy-Recording Secretary, 1936
- Woods Run, Jeanette C. Kennedy-Reports, Statements, Correspondence, 1935-1939
- Woods Run, Jeanette C. Kennedy-Financial Statements Reports, 1937, 1939
- Woods Run, General Conditions of the Work
- Woods Run, Resident Director, May 1, 1912
- Woods Run, Resident Director, October 27, 1913
- Woods Run, Resident Director, November 21, 1913
- Woods Run, Resident Director, Read at Regular Board Meeting, December 22, 1913
- Woods Run, Resident Director, 1914-1915
- Roll Book, 1919-1920
- Roll Book, 1920-1921
- Club Leaders Weekly Attendance Record Report, 1919
- Piano Pupils Weekly Attendance Record Report, 1919
- Piano Department, 1921
- Music (Weekly Attendance Record Report), 1917-1918
- Evening Class In English, Weekly Attendance Record Report, 1920
- Resolution, May 2, 1914 (Box 4)
- Reports, meetings, and correspondence, 1938
- Meetings and reports, 1940
- Miscellaneous Reports, 1935-1941
- Last Will and Testament of John Poterfield, Deceased, Resolutions, correspondence and reports
- Application to Welfare Fund for paid worker in Personnel Department
- Fresh Air Farms (Glenfield) - Correspondence, 1915
- Correspondence-National Board of the Young Women's Christian Associations of the United States of America-Department of Immigration Foreign Communities, 1931
- Woods Run Settlement-Dept. Reports Statistical Information, 1913-14, 1937-1941
- Reports(Miscellaneous) Woods Run Settlement, 1931-32, 1936-38
- Miscellaneous Correspondence, reports pamphlets
- A Brief Summary of Activities and Attendance-Westhall Annex, 1948-1949 (Box 5)
- Woods Run School
- Woods Run School-Soc. Education Action Baby Clinic
- Steps I VI
- Blueprints
- Board Building-Maintenance (3 folders), 1927-1940
- Building Contract Receipts-Annual Meeting, May 22, 1917
- Board Committees
- Material for New Board Members (3 folders)
- Summary of Findings of Tuberculosis in Woods Run
- Bath (showers) Study, 1934-44
- Pre-school Activities Report, 1948-1949
- Report of Committee of Federations of Social Agencies on W.R.S, Lawrenceville Neighborhood House Soho Public Baths. At request of Mayor David L.Lawrence, 1947 (Box 6)
- Survey of Verner, July, 1940
- Soho Public Baths, September, 1947
- Lawrenceville Neighborhood House, September, 1947
- Social Statistics Project-Form G
- Woods Run Settlement-Schedules Activities
- Woods Run Settlement-Day Nursery Data
- Nursery Statistics, June 1, 1923-1924
- Woods Run Settlements-Neighborhood Beautification Projects. Daily Field Reports, June-July, 1939
- Mabel K. Day
- Material for Report to Mayor Lawrence (2 folders)
- History-Personal Notes (Box 7)
- Old Booklets Reports (2 folders), 1930
- Woods Run Settlement-Miscellaneous (5 folders)
- Miscellaneous (3 folders)
- Stationery, Envelopes
- Camp Bonsall Study, 1929-1943
- Statistical Summary, 1938-1939
- Camp Bonsall, Construction, 1939-1941
- Camp Bonsall, Petty Cash (3 folders), 1943-45
- Camp Bonsall, (2 folders), 1940-42, 1946-47
- Camp Bonsall, Work Crews, 1934
- Camp Bonsall, Staff, 1949
- Camp Bonsall, (2 folders), nd
- Camp Bonsall, Notes, 1934-37 (Box 9)
- Camp Bonsall, Notes, 1937-38
- Camp Bonsall, Correspondence, 1925-26
- Camp Bonsall, Farm
- Camp Bonsall, Farm, 1948-1949
- Camp Bonsall, Farm Project
- Camp Bonsall, Publicity, 1945
- Camp Bonsall, Miscellaneous
- Report of the Nature Study Activity Program Pittsburgh-Riverview Park, Summer, 1943
- The Community Garden Experiment of the Woods Run Settlement by Ralph E. Griswold, 1940
- Neighbor Garden Club
- Woods Run Settlement-50th Year (Box 10)
- Papyrus, 1939-1940
- Tattler (3 folders), 1930, 1932-38, 1950-51, 1953
- Victory News, 1942, 1945-46
- Junior Journal, December, 1936
- Round Table, March, 1943
- Kingsley Record, Dec. 19, 1924 - June, 1946
- Forecaster, May, 1943
- Adult Leadership, March, 1954-April, 1954
- Village News, 1939
- The Federation, April, 1938
- Service Directory for New American, by American Service Institute
- Kingsley Portrait, 1893 -1952
- Directory of Psychological Services in Pittsburgh Area, January, 1953
- The Valley Speaks-leaflet
- The Past Is Prelude, 1953
- Community Council Bulletin, May, 1939
- Allied Youth, October, 1945
- Pitt
- Downtown Y News, June, 1946
- The News (Boys' Club of Pgh., Inc.), 1937, 1946
- Miscellaneous Leaflets
- Reports of Associations, Centers, and Federations, etc. (miscellaneous) (3 folders) (Box 11)
- Statistical Report-Study for Service Area no. XVI-Brighton Woods, 1938
- University Settlement-56th 57th Annual Report
- Pittsburgh Ledger, July 5, 1940
- Newspaper Clippings
- Youth Leaders Digest, October, 1953
- George Williams College Bulletin, May 15, 1946
- The Settlement As A Community Force by A.J. Bonsall
- Programs (miscellaneous)
- City and Suburban Life, Sept. 26, 1914, May 8, 1915, July 31, 1915
- Irene Kaufmann Settlement
- Juvenile Court of Allegheny County, 1945 (Box 12)
- Settlements-National Federation etc.
- Athletic Federation
- Map No. 4- Lowland Slopes and Highland With Playspaces
- Pittsburgh Playgrounds by Citizens of Pittsburgh on City Planning, 1920
- Social Facts Contrasting with Pittsburgh, 1941
- Plan for Community action
- Flood Write-up pictures
- Flood, Jan. 22, 1937
- Flood Information (miscellaneous)
- Flood-St. Patrick's Day, 1936
- Flood Building Repairs Equipment, 1936
- Floods, 27.7 feet and 33.4 feet, February 27, 1945, March 7, 1945
- Floods, Dec. 29, 1942, Jan. 2, 1943
- Social Conditions in the Twenty-Seventh Ward by Albert J. Kennedy, 1930 (Box 13)
- Study of the 27th Ward. Maps, tables and Source Material. Parts I and II
- Neighborhood-A Settlement Quarterly(12 issues), 1928-1932 (Box 14)
- Each Tomorrow by George William Gerwig, St. Petersburg, Florida
- Suggested Procedures for Developing Good Intercultural and Interracial Practices in Group Work and Recreation Agencies by the American Service Institute of Allegheny County
- Music Schools and Settlement Music Departments by Janet D. Schenck, Boston, 1923
- An Appraisal of Camp Facilities by H.O. Whiteside
- Citizens Committee on City Plan of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh Playgrounds, June, 1920
- Disaster Sub-Survey American Red Cross Zone 14 Survey by Harry Workmaster
- Woods Run Minute Books, 1895-1939 (Box 15)
- Miscellaneous Records of Miss Jeanette Kennedy, Recording Secretary and others. Woods Run Industrial House, 1895-1911 (Box 16)
- and a few Clippings, 1912-13 1914-1916
- Roll Book of Piano Pupils, September, 1922-1923
- Woods Run Settlement Guide Book, 1914-1917
- Scrapbook of Newspaper Clippings
- Minutes